Guide to the Herbert Morawetz Collection RG.037
Poly Archives at the Bern Dibner Library of Science and Technology, NYU Libraries
Herbert Morawetz Collection
1943-2017
Poly Archives at the Bern Dibner Library of Science and Technology, NYU Libraries
RG.037
4.5 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes, 2 thin manuscript boxes, 2 cartons, and 1 oversized box.
23.1 Megabytes in 3 Google Drive folders.
The Herbert Morawetz collection contains published and unpublished materials related to the career and scholarship of 20th century polymer chemist Herbert Morawetz including correspondence, awards and honors, copies of books and articles, and personal, autobiographical writing.
Biographical / Historical
Herbert Morawetz (b.1915-d.2017) was a Brooklyn-based polymer chemist and professor specializing in the use of fluorescence spectroscopy to study local conformational transitions and polymer compatibility. After fleeing his home country of Czechoslovakia with his family following German occupation in 1939, Morawetz settled in Canada, earning Bachelor's (1943) and Master's (1945) degrees in Chemical Engineering from the University of Toronto and a PhD (1950) in Chemistry from the Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn (later becoming the Tandon School of Engineering at NYU in 2014). In 1951, he joined the faculty at Poly where he would spend the duration of his career, becoming the director of the Polymer Research Institute in 1971.
He published two major books: "Macromolecules in Solution," in 1965 and "Polymers: The Origins and Growth of a Science" in 1985. In 1986, Morawetz received the American Chemical Society Award in Polymer Chemistry and following his retirement from teaching, spent fifteen years as the editor of the scholarly journal "Macromolecules". He was the husband of prominent mathematician Cathleen Synge Morawetz. Herbert Morawetz passed away in November 2017, a few weeks after his 102nd birthday.
Scope and Contents
The Herbert Morawetz collection contains published and unpublished materials related to the career and scholarship of 20th century polymer chemist Herbert Morawetz. Contents include: correspondence with other professionals and colleagues; photographs of Morawetz and colleagues; invitations and documentation of events and awards ceremonies attended by or honoring Morawetz; Morawetz's personal writing including an unpublished autobiography and a travel diary detailing a visit to Prague in 1979; personal correspondence, media coverage and public facing material related to the 1978 boycott of the International Symposium on Macromolecular Chemistry in Tashkent, Uzbekistan (then USSR); administrative documents regarding Morawetz's employment at the Polymer Research Institute; and copies of published articles and books by Morawetz or owned by him, in English and multiple foreign languages.
Arrangement
Materials were organized by form and content type into seven series: Biographical, Correspondence, Writings, Photographs, Awards and Honors, Publications, and Digitized Items. Some materials are arranged chronologically at the item level.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Bulk of materials donated by John Morawetz, son of Herbert Morawetz in 2018. Items collected from Herbert Morawetz's former home, 246 West 12th St., New York, NY. Digital copies of items transferred via email by John. Previous accession was donated by Chemical Heritage Foundation in 2016. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 18.001 and 16.006.
Alternate Form Available
Some materials from the Biographical and Photographs series were digitized by John Morawetz, son of Herbert Morawetz, and are available in the Digitized Items series.
Polymer engineering; Polymer science and technology; World War, 1939-1945--Science; Photographs; Correspondence; Books; Autobiographies (literary works); Awards; Translations (documents)
- Series I: Biographical (Box 1)
  - Biographical - Sketches, 1985-2005 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical - "My 90 Years," Autobiography, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biographical - Czechoslovak Diary, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Biographical - Morawetz Interview by James Bohning, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Memorial Service Materials, 2017 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series II: Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Correspondence - Personal, 1956-1999, bulk 1960s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence & Materials - Birthday Wishes and Celebration Materials, 1981-2015, bulk 1995 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence - Professional, 1943-2005 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence - 1978 Boycott of Conference in Tashkent (USSR), 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence - Salary and Appointment at PIB, 1951-1986 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence & Materials - Lectures and Conferences, 1957-2006 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence - Reprint Request Cards, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series III: Writings (Box 1)
  - Eulogies and Toasts by Morawetz, 1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - PRESENTATION NOTES (incl. overhead slides), undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Recollection of Fritz Eirich, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Series IV: Photographs (Box 2, Box 3, Oversize 7)
  - Photo album, undated (Box 2, Item 1)
  - Photobook - "Dr. Herbert Morawetz' 96th Birthday Party", 2011 (Box 2, Item 2-3)
    General
    Two copies.
  - PHOTOGRAPHS - By occasion, May 1998, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - PHOTOGRAPHS - Small, 1957-1997, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - PHOTOGRAPHS - Midsize, 1953-1989, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - PHOTOGRAPHS - Oversize and photocopies, 1975-2006, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Slide tray, "Solid State Org. Reactions", undated (Box 3, Item 1)
  - Framed photo of Morawetz with students in front of Polytechnic Institute of New York building, May 1981 (Oversize 7, Item 3)
  - Framed image of Herman Mark with nearly illegible writing: "With best wishes and [....], H. Mark", undated (Oversize 7, Item 4)
- Series V: Awards and Honors (Oversize 7, Box 2)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Tightly rolled scroll, possibly Herbert Morawetz's University of Toronto diplomas, is in need of conservation and is not open to researchers.
  - Formal congratulations for his 80th birthday from Poly Chancellor David C. Chang, 1995 (Box 2, Item 4)
  - Awards and Honors, 1984-2006 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Sesquicentennial PolyThinker medal, 2005 (Oversize 7, Item 1)
  - Tightly rolled scroll (possibly contains at least one diploma from the University of Toronto), undated (Oversize 7, Item 2)
  - American Chemical Society plaque for service as Associated Editor of "Macromolecules" from 1991-2005 (Oversize 7, Item 5)
  - American Chemical Society Award in Polymer Chemistry, 1986 (Oversize 7, Item 6)
  - Honorary degree from the University of Rome "La Sapienza", 2006 (Oversize 7, Item 7)
  - International Symposium on Macromolecules, 1977-07-17-1977-07-22 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series VI: Publications (Box 4, Carton 5, Carton 6)
  - PUBLICATIONS - 151-182 & Index, 1983-1988 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - PUBLICATIONS - 183-210, 1988-2004 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Book Reviews - "Polymers: The Origins and Growth of a Science", 1985-1986, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Foreign Language Materials, 2008, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - "Publications of H. Morawetz: Nos. 1-32", 1949-1958 (Carton 5, Item 1)
  - "Publications of H. Morawetz: Nos. 33-63", 1958-1963 (Carton 5, Item 2)
  - "Publications: Nos. 1-63, 1949-63. H. Morawetz", 1949-1963 (Carton 5, Item 3)
  - "Publications of H. Morawetz: Nos. 64-100", 1964-1971 (Carton 5, Item 4-5)
  - "H. Morawetz: Publications 101-150", 1971-1983 (Carton 5, Item 6-7)
  - "Sulphur Dioxide Recovery," Bachelor's Thesis by H. Morawetz, April 1943 (Carton 5, Item 8)
  - "The Counter-Ion Distribution in Solutions of Partially Neutralized Polymeric Acids: The Preparation and Preliminary Evaluation of Some Amphoteric Polyelectrolytes," PhD Dissertation by Herbert Morawetz, September 1950 (Carton 5, Item 9-10)
  - "Chování makromolekul v roztoku" by Herbert Morawetz, 1971 (Carton 5, Item 11)
  - "Macromolecules in Solution" by Herbert Morawetz, 1965 (Carton 5, Item 12)
  - Translation of "Polymers: The Origins and Growth of a Science" by Herbert Morawetz, in Arabic script, undated (Carton 5, Item 13)
  - "Polymers: The Origins and Growth of a Science" by Herbert Morawetz (Hardcover, Wiley), 1985 (Carton 6, Item 1-2)
  - "Polymers: The Origins and Growth of a Science" by Herbert Morawetz (Paperback, Dover), 1995 (Carton 6, Item 3)
  - "Polymers: The Origins and Growth of a Science" by Herbert Morawetz (Hardcover, Dover), 2002 (Carton 6, Item 4)
  - "Macromolecules in Solution" by Herbert Morawetz, 1965 (Carton 6, Item 5)
  - "Macromolecules in Solution" by Herbert Morawetz (Reprint), 1966 (Carton 6, Item 6)
  - "Macromolecules in Solution" by Herbert Morawetz (2nd ed.), 1975 (Carton 6, Item 7)
  - "Macromolecules in Solution" by Herbert Morawetz (Personal copy - Reprint of the 2nd ed.), 1983 (Carton 6, Item 8)
    Hardcover author's copy of the 1983 corrected reprinting of the second edition of "Macromolecules in Solution," Vol. 21 in the series "High Polymer". Pages are all detached from binding and include Morawetz's notes, cut and taped-in sections, and are partially out of order. Side is stamped "Department of Chemistry, Polytechnic Institute of New York"
  - "Macromolecules in Solution" by Herbert Morawetz (Reprint of the 2nd ed.), 1983 (Carton 6, Item 9)
  - "Thesen zur Größe und Struktur der Makromoleküle" by Claus Preisner (Personal copy with notes), 1980 (Carton 6, Item 10)
  - "Der Aufbau der hochpolymeren organischen Naturstoffe" by Kurt H. Meyer and Herman Mark, 1930 (Carton 6, Item 11)
  - "高分子科學技術發展簡史 / Gao fen zi ke xue ji shu fa zhan jian shi" by Baogong Qian, Luoli Wang, and Xiayu Wang, 1994 (Carton 6, Item 12)
  - "макромолекулы в растворе / Makromolekuly v rastvore" by Herbert Morawetz, 1967 (Carton 6, Item 13)
  - "Fizykochemia roztworów makrocząsteczek" by Herbert Morawetz, 1970 (Carton 6, Item 14)
  - "Polyelectrolyte Solutions: A Theoretical Introduction" by Stuart Rice and Mitsuru Nagasawa with a contribution by Herbert Morawetz, 1961 (Carton 6, Item 15)
- Series VII: Digitized Items
  Alternate Form Available
  Digital copies of items transferred in 2018 via email by John Morawetz, son of Herbert Morawetz.
  Some items are digitized versions of physical items in the Herbert Morawetz collection and some are only present in a digitized form. The digitized items are all located in Poly Archivist Lindsay Anderberg's Google Drive folders.
  - Artwork, 1989; 1998; Undated
  - Photographs, Undated
  - Text, Undated; 2006